Guide to the Melvin Hedine Papers 1930-1972
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
Melvin Hedine Papers
1930-1972
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana--Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 443
Hedine, Melvin, 1913-1982
0.25 linear feet
Melvin Hedine was a journalist and photographer who graduated from the University of Montana. The collection includes correspondence, clippings, and photographs, 1930-1972.
Biographical Note
Melvin "Dutch" Hedine was born on December 29, 1913, in Montana. His parents were Alfred and Josephine Hedine. Hedine graduated from Missoula County High School and attended the University of Montana. At the university, he was active with the Masquers drama club theatre productions between 1930 and 1935. Hedine graduated with a Bachelor of Arts degree in Journalism in 1935. Hedine went on to receive a P.P.A. from the Los Angeles Art Center School and an Education Credential at Los Angeles State College. During World War II, he served as a U.S. Army combat photographer. In the early 1950s, he remained in the U.S. armed services.
Melvin Hedine went on to work as a technical illustrator at Hoffmann Electronics, Miller Dial, and Lockheed Aircraft Co. He was also involved in producing educational filmstrips and national display photography. Hedine had photography accounts with such companies as Chanel, Sunkist, and Max Factor. He was a senior precision photographer at Northrop Laboratories for a period of time. At Northrop, Hedine worked on electronic circuitry and in the early 1960s, he developed new procedures to reduce photograph development time. Hedine died on May 7, 1982 and is buried at Riverside National Cemetery in Escondido, CA.
The collection includes correspondence, clippings, and photographs, 1930-1972. The clippings are from Missoula County High School and University of Montana drama productions, 1930 to 1934, including programs, production notes, and Montana Kaimin clippings. The collection includes photographs taken of Melvin Hedine and his family and of University of Montana drama productions. There are also photographs presumably taken during Hedine's career in the armed services around the 1940s or 1950s. The collection also includes samples of Hedine's display photography and photographs taken by Hedine during his laboratory career, c. 1960s.
The collection is divided into three series:
Series I: Correspondence, 4 items, circa 1940-1972
Series II: Clippings, 24 items, 1930-1934
Series III: Photographs, 45 photographs, ca. 1930-1950
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana--Missoula.
Gift of Edna Hedine Grape, 1992 and 1993
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Missoula County High School; University of Montana--Missoula; University of Montana--Missoula--Alumni and alumnae
United States--Armed Forces--Photographers
College and school drama, American--Montana--Missoula; College theater--Montana--Missoula; Commercial photography--United States; Photography, Military--United States
Clippings; Photographs
Photographs; Colleges and Universities; Journalism; Military
Photographers--Montana--Missoula; Photographers--United States
Montana Kaimin
- Correspondence, circa 1940-1972; Series I; 4 items
  The series contains an illustrated letter from Melvin to his sister, Viola, while he was in the armed services, a letter of recommendation from an art institution, 1952, and two letters pertaining to a patent on an invention by Hedine, 1972.
  - Correspondence, ca. 1940s-1972 (Box-folder 1/1)
- Clippings, 1930-1934; Series II; 24 items
  The series contains clippings from Missoula County High School and University of Montana drama productions. The clippings include newspaper articles from the Montana Kaimin, production notes and one set diagram. The bulk of the clippings are programs from productions in which Hedine was involved.
  - Drama Production clippings, 1930-1934 (Box-folder 1/2)
- Photographs, circa 1930-1950; Series III; 45 photographs
  Most of the photographs in the series are from University of Montana Masquers productions in which Hedine was involved. The photographs of stage sets labeled "designed by Dutch," refer to Hedine. There are also two professional photographs of studio films. The armed services photographs were presumably taken by Melvin Hedine during World War II. There are photographs of Bob Hope and other performers taken during U.S.O. performances and of Melvin Hedine in uniform. There are also photographs presumably of display advertising. Some of these are in color.
  The photographs are arranged by subject and date. The photographs begin with UM drama productions, followed by armed services, family photographs, and end with various other photographs related to Hedine's career.
  - Play, location unknown, undated; 443(III)1 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - "R.U.R."-a Masquers play, 1932; 443(III)2 (Box-folder 1/4)
  - "Children of the Moon", a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)3 (Box-folder 1/5)
  - "Children of the Moon," a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)4 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - "Children of the Moon," a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)5 (Box-folder 1/7)
  - "The Taming of the Shrew", 1933; 443(III)6 (Box-folder 1/8)
  - "The Taming of the Shrew", 1933; 443(III)7 (Box-folder 1/9)
  - "Dr. Knock", a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)8 (Box-folder 1/10)
  - "Dr. Knock," a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)9 (Box-folder 1/11)
  - "Dr. Knock" set, a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)10 (Box-folder 1/12)
  - "Dr. Knock" a Masquers play, 1933; 443(III)11 (Box-folder 1/13)
  - "The Front Page," a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)12 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - "The Noble Gesture," a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)13 (Box-folder 1/15)
  - "The Tavern" a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)14 (Box-folder 1/16)
  - "The Tavern" a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)15 (Box-folder 1/17)
  - "Twelfth Night," a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)16 (Box-folder 1/18)
  - "Twelfth Night," a Masquers play, 1934; 443(III)17 (Box-folder 1/19)
  - DeMirjian, New York, NY, undated; 443(III)18 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Warner Bros. Productions Corporation Picture, Reinhardt's "A Midsummer Night's Dream", undated; 443(III)19 (Box-folder 1/21)
  - Bob Hope and USO performers, undated; 443(III)20 (Box-folder 1/22)
  - Bob Hope and band, undated; 443(III)21 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Bob Hope and performer at USO performance, undated; 443(III)22 (Box-folder 1/24)
  - Pianist at USO performance, undated; 443(III)23 (Box-folder 1/25)
  - Buzz Bomb Alley Siege, undated; 443(III)24 (Box-folder 1/26)
  - Plane on ground, location unknown, undated; 443(III)25 (Box-folder 1/27)
  - Melvin Hedine in uniform, undated; 443(III)26 (Box-folder 1/28)
  - Melvin Hedine in uniform with soldier, undated; 443(III)27 (Box-folder 1/29)
  - Melvin Hedine (reclining) and two men in uniform, undated; 443(III)28 (Box-folder 1/30)
  - Melvin Hedine in uniform in front of lion statue, undated; 443(III)29 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Melvin Hedine in uniform in front of tank, undated; 443(III)30 (Box-folder 1/32)
  - Melvin, Emma, Edna, and Alfred Hedine, 1930; 433(III)31 (Box-folder 1/33)
  - Melvin Hedine, undated; 443(III)32 (Box-folder 1/34)
  - Cottage, location unknown, undated; 443(III)33 (Box-folder 1/35)
  - Partial biography of Melvin Hedine (transparency), undated; 443(III)34 (Box-folder 1/36)
  - Pen and ink drawing by Melvin Hedine, undated; 443(III)35 (Box-folder 1/37)
  - Northrop facility, Palos Verde, CA (color photo), 1963; 443(III)36 (Box-folder 1/38)
  - Dye transfer (color photo), undated; 443(III)37 (Box-folder 1/39)
  - Woman on flexichrome skis (promotional photo) (color), undated; 443(III)38 (Box-folder 1/40)
  - Man with scientific instrument, undated; 443(III)39 (Box-folder 1/41)
  - Merrill's Fine Soap (promotional photo), undated; 443(III)40 (Box-folder 1/42)
  - Gas gauge in facility, undated; 443(III)41 (Box-folder 1/43)
  - Carnation in vase and glass jar with colored dye (color photo), undated; 443(III)42 (Box-folder 1/44)
  - Scientist with test tube, undated; 443(III)43 (Box-folder 1/45)
  - Woman asleep and cooling device (?) (promotional photo), undated; 443(III)44 (Box-folder OS1/1)
  - Ciroflex photography camera (promotional photo), undated; 443(III)45 (Box-folder OS1/2)